Last month, about two weeks ago,
a British journalist called Steve
Sweeney, who lives and works
in Beirut, Lebanon,
was in southern Lebanon,
attempting with a cameraman to
document what the Israeli military
is doing to the southern part of
that country, which is
leveling it, moving people
wholesale out, including Christian
villages across the area.
And as he was preparing his report,
he was targeted
by an Israeli-owned American-made
aircraft that fired a missile at
him in an attempted assassination.
Here's what it looked like.
Further rocket attacks were reported
against Nahariya, and a minute...
FUCKING OOF
FUCK
That wasn't an accident, it was
intentional.
The jet that fired it had flown
over his position, attempting
to assassinate him as the Israeli
government has assassinated on
purpose, not accidentally
assassinated, murdered so
many journalists, including Western
journalists trying to cover its
atrocities, atrocities that
are spreading even
now under the cover of the Iran War,
a massive land grab across the
region, killing of
Christians, desecration of Christian
holy sites.
That's all happening.
It's all real and one of the reasons
you may not know about it is because
the people trying to record it to
Chronicle it have been assassinated
But Steve Sweeney was not
assassinated by luck
or the grace of god By
a quirk of the landing of
that missile. He survived He
joins us now to explain what
happened Steve, thanks very
much for doing this.
I'm grateful. You're alive Can
you we just played the tape of
the moment where you were almost
killed. Can you?
Add context to that and describe
what was happening.
Well, yeah, you've seen the
footage and we were
incredibly lucky to come out of that
situation alive.
It was only purely by luck that
the missile ended up, as
you've see on the footage, it
went... Through the hole and
the bridge had already been
destroyed. So just to give you some
context of why
we were there, Israel had
issued these evacuation orders.
It said that it was going to bomb
every single bridge in
south Lebanon. So the bridges across
the Latani River, this connects
the south of Lebanon to the rest of
the country. So this was a hugely
important news stories,
this is essentially cutting off.
You know, a whole swathe of
the country.
And they'd started the bombing the
night before. It was a Thursday when
we went to the bridge.
On the Wednesday evening and into
the early hours of the morning,
they'd starting targeting the
bridges. So...
As a journalist and as a war
correspondent, we were
there to report on this
huge news story.
So we drove down, this is in Soor
district or Tire district as
other people will probably better
know it, and as
we approached the Lebanese army have
a base there, just
ahead of the bridge.
So we approached them and we said to
them, okay, is it safe
to film?
And they assured us it was
perfectly safe for us to go on that
bridge and they would
know because if Israel is about
to bomb a bridge, which they had
already bombed it the night before,
then they would get a message to
the Lebanese army via UNIFIL,
the United Nations peacekeepers.
They don't have direct
communication.
So there was no pre-warning that
this bridge was about to be struck
again. There was no military
objective in striking the bridge
again. It was already destroyed.
There was you could barely even walk
across it, let alone take a vehicle
across it. So this was the the
Kazmir bridge.
This was the smaller bridge.
So these kind of link villages
and settlements in south Lebanon
together.
So, OK, we we approached
the bridge. We set up our camera.
We started filming.
There were fighter jets roaring
overhead.
And again this isn't uncommon in
the south of Lebanon but we
knew that the fighter jets were
flying away from us so they were
roaring overhead but they were
heading further south
and they were bombing what they
would describe as Hezbollah
positions around that
area so we weren't still unduly
concerned and we went onto the
bridge and we started
filming so it wasn't live some
people have said it was live it was
what call it as live.
So we were filming
that.
We arrived on the bridge.
I was doing my piece of camera.
He went to film
some b-roll.
He went to films in the hole
where the bridge had been struck.
We talk about luck and we talk about
chance and we talk about
God's will, but as
he was filming, there was a gust of
wind on the camera and the tripod
was shaking.
So I called him over and I
I said Ali, please come,
the camera is shaking, I need you
to steady it.
As he came over, I guess
around 15 seconds later,
then we heard this tremendous roar
and the Israelis struck
the bridge again.
And I mean, the immediate
aftermath, I mean I remember just
thinking, God, we're dead.
That was it.
It was like
this earth shattering sound.
The explosion, it was an almighty
blast. And then there was just
dust and I couldn't really see
anything.
From the footage you can hear the
soldiers maybe they started saying
to me yalla yalla and I couldn't see
anything so I was where
where.
And they took me into
their barracks.
They put tourniquets on my arms.
I thought, again with the adrenaline
rush, I just thought I've got some
minor cuts.
I couldn't really feel too much pain
but then I looked where they put the
tournique. There was blood coming
down my arms, there was blood on
my clothes but I was alive
and it's
again completely by chance we were
alive. This was a very heavy
munition that they'd use a GBU-38.
Um missile that we believe was used
it was fired from an f-16
fighter jet so after
the lebanese army were uh
you know they put these uh
tourniquets on and gave us some
water uh then they called
an ambulance and the
ambulance came and they put
me on a stretcher and they uh off
off they took me and i should know
really that the
paramedics and the emergency workers
and the doctors and the nurses and
all of the medical team that
attended to us are the
real heroes of this story.
As we were traveling from the bridge
to the hospital, I'm not sure the
distance, maybe about 10 minutes,
probably less than that, but they
had the blue lights on.
Now in any normal country
anywhere in the world having the
blue light on and being transported
somewhere by ambulance, you would
safe, right?
Not in Lebanon, because the
Israelis are now targeting
medical staff.
More than 50 have been killed.
Hospitals, including the one we
attended, the Jabal Amal hospital,
part of that has
been destroyed in Israeli
airstrikes.
And we've been working in the field
for many years now.
We're very experienced journalists
and we take safety very seriously.
We've spoken to a lot of medical
workers and
they told us that the
logo on the top of the ambulances
which is supposed to give them
protection under international
law, under the Geneva conventions
and this kind of thing, instead of
giving them protection it
now places them at risk.
So many of them have removed those
logos from their
emergency vehicles.
Barely a day goes by now that when
we don't hear of a medical worker
being struck,
the IDF, the Israeli Defense
Force... Soon after they carried
out a massacre of 12 emergency
workers in the
south, targeting their
station, they put out a
statement saying that
Hezbollah is using
medical facilities and
ambulances for military purposes.
Now, of course, they didn't back
that with any kind of evidence.
This is a statement that they've
reissued again quite recently,
but ... Yeah, we've been on the
ground. We've been in the back of
the ambulances. We have been in the
hospitals.
We met the civil defense
workers. We meet the paramedics and
we have been to these stations and
all that you can see there are
the kind of things that you would
find in any hospital, in any medical
station, in ambulance anywhere
in the world. These are
medical facilities there
and they should be protected under
international law.
Of course, targeting these
deliberately is a war crime but
it is just one of many that we are
seeing.
Here on the ground in Lebanon.
You're probably thinking about where
to shop for Mother's Day.
Cozy Earth, obviously the answer
designed for moms who make houses
feel like homes.
Cozy earth creates comfort for the
entire day between bedding,
sleepwear, towels, lounge wear,
and a lot more, you will find a
great Mother's day gift there.
You could wear the Cozy-Earth bamboo
pajama set, which is
hilarious, but also great.
It's literally made out of bamboo,
and it's a huge upgrade over what
you're probably wearing.
It's light, soft,
doesn't overheat.
Right now, Cozy Earth is doing
something they never do, a buy one,
get one deal. These pajamas are so
good that they sold out during
Christmas, they are back now.
This deal goes from April 6th
to the 12th of April.
Visit CozyEarth.com today.
Use the code TUCKERBOGO,
that's Tucker B-O-G-O, to get
these pajamas for you and a loved
one. Plus, there's a 100 night sleep
trial and a 10 year warranty, so
there's zero risk.
By the way, if you get a survey
after, feel free to mention you
heard about Cozy earth here.
So you're a Westerner.
It's by your accent, you sound
Irish.
Um, you live and
work in Lebanon. How long have you
been there?
I came to Lebanon in
October 2024.
So this was during the period we
call the 66 Day War.
So it was a
week or so after the
assassination of Saeed Hassan
Nasrallah.
Former Secretary General of
Hezbollah.
So I came then, we quite
often joke and say that if Steve
Sweeney arrives in your country,
then it's not good news.
But I came during
that period.
Now, Lebanon, as you know, and I
think I've heard you say Tucker, if
I'm correct,
it's a beautiful country.
Oh, the most.
Wonderful place.
You know, you look at the rich
culture, tradition and history of
this country even in
the south now which is the area
coming under heavy bombardment.
This is the area of Jesus.
Kana is where Jesus
performed what I believe was his
first miracle, turning water into
wine.
There's the tomb of Shemun
Ar-Saffah, this is Peter Simon,
St. Peter, who I
think for many Catholics they
believe that he was the first pope.
Now that's where some
Christians believe that that's his
burial site.
Of course, this has been destroyed
by Israel, they bombed it.
This is an important site actually,
Shemu Ar-saffah for both Muslims
and Christians, so that's been
bombed, but so I was...
Wait a minute, let me have-
Wait, let me ask you to stop for a
second, and I'm ashamed by my
ignorance as usual.
The Israeli military bombed St.
Peter's burial site?
When? I did.
This was back in 2024.
This wasn't an accidental bombing.
I think
it's protected under world heritage
law as well.
And it's a very important site.
Of course, the
burial place of Saint Peter is
also a holy site for
Muslims. And what they did during
that period was they brought an
Israeli, what they call a
researcher, the Israeli Defense
Force, brought him in.
And the purpose of that really
was to, I
guess, reinvent history.
And the aim of it was to say,
well, this is a Jewish holy site
and this land belongs
to Israel. This was the kind of
narrative that they were trying
to spin. That researcher, who was
actually a very well-known
settler activist,
was killed during that time.
We visited the
site in early
2025 after the ceasefire
period and missiles
have gone through the domes,
the whole area was destroyed, bullet
marks
across all of the buildings there,
including the area of the
shrine of Saint Peter himself.
So this wasn't
accidentally targeted,
it wasn't kind of collateral damage,
This was a deliberately targeted
attack.
On the tomb of Saint Peter.
It's not the only church
or religious
building that has been attacked, of
course. We were in a place called
Derdegaia and this
is a Greek
Catholic church and again
that was destroyed during
the 66 day war.
They killed eight people that had
taken shelter inside there.
A lot of those were emergency
workers, the civil defense team,
and they'd taken shelter there and
they bombed it to oblivion.
It was completely destroyed.
And again in Yaroun,
this is another border town
and there are two
buildings there.
There's the Imam Ali Mosque,
which is a very well-known mosque in
the south of Lebanon, but there was
also the Church of St
George.
And St George, of course, the patron
saint of England,
and this was a Catholic Church and
they're very close by each other.
And you may have seen the footage
circulating on social
media, but there's footage
of an Israeli soldier, I guess, with
a body cam or something,
a helmet cam, destroying
the statue there to
St. George. But both of those were
completely destroyed.
So what's interesting is that...
Hezbollah is, and I'm not defending
Hezballah, it's not my fight,
but they're designated, I believe,
by the US government as a terror
group. They've controlled big parts
of Lebanon for many, many years,
more than 20 years.
And has Hezbalah blown up
Christian holy sites?
Has Hezbolah targeted
ambulances?
I mean, maybe they have.
You live there. You tell me.
No, they haven't.
In fact, the opposite.
And again, there's plenty of footage
of this that people can
check for themselves online.
But Hezbollah was in fact protecting
the Christian churches and
protecting these
kind of symbolic
areas of religious importance
to Christians.
There's footage of them going into
churches and cleaning up and tidying
up and standing around protecting
the Christian faith.
If you listen to the speeches of
Hassan Nasrallah, again,
he said the Hezbollah are the main
defenders of the Christian faith in
Lebanon.
So no, they're not destroying
ambulances, they are not destroying
churches, they are destroying
mosques, they aren't destroying
people's homes, but Israel is
and it's doing it with American
and Western supplied weapons as
well.
And it's happening without
anybody, pretty much anybody
in the United States even noticing.
I think people's attention is drawn
to what's happening in Iran and the
unfolding disaster there, and they
don't even know that this is
happening. So back to what happened
to you specifically, you
said that the missile that almost
killed you and your cameraman was
launched from an American aircraft,
an Israeli-owned American
aircraft.
Do you believe, was
that one of the planes that had
flown over you?
Do you think it was targeting you?
Undoubtedly, we believe it was
targeting us.
There could be no other explanation
for what happened now.
Of course, because people have asked
this question, why
were you on the bridge and were
you deliberately targeted?
And we're unequivocal about that.
This was an assassination attempt by
Israel to silence the
voices on the ground, to silence the
truth. Now, the reason we say that
is because, like I said, we've
been working in the for the
last two years.
So our vehicle is very well known in
the south of Lebanon.
We were in a clearly identified
press vehicle.
We had, as you can see in the
footage, we had our press jackets
on.
Israel has the most advanced
military technology anywhere in the
world. It has the more advanced
surveillance technology anywhere in
the World. It knows everything that
happens in the South of Lebanon.
It knows every vehicle.
It knows every number plate.
It reads our messages.
It listens to our conversations.
This is why we say it was
deliberate, because there's no doubt
that they knew we were there.
And the other issue, as has been
raised by the Russian Foreign
Ministry, Maria Zaharova, said that
this can't have been accidental.
There was no military objective in
targeting that bridge.
It was already destroyed.
So we believe it was a deliberate
assassination attempt.
Absolutely.
And it's only by luck, really.
That we survived.
There was a lot going in our favor
that day.
Let's say, had the missile not
entered the hole in the bridge, had
it exploded on the bridge...
And we've spoken to military
experts, weapons experts who have
told us that if it had been
maybe a few inches or
a foot the other way, then there
wouldn't have even been bodies to
recover. We'd have just been
incinerated. These are incredibly
powerful munitions that they were
using.
And there was no military objective,
as I've said, in targeting the
bridge. So we say that we were
deliberately targeted by
the Israelis without a doubt.
You go into the grocery store and
there are endless snacks and
protein bars.
Paleo Valley Superfood bars are, we
think, the best.
Most nutrition bars seem healthy,
but then you read the labels and it
turns out they're packed with all
kinds of bizarre stuff.
Processed syrups, ingredients you
can't pronounce.
They're essentially candy, masked
by marketers pretending they're
healthy.
I've eaten a lot of them, I would
know. Paleo Valley Superfood bars
are different though.
Paleo Valley makes its products with
real ingredients like organic
fruits, vegetables, nuts,
seeds, or no seed oils, soy, gluten,
other weird additives, and
you know when you finish eating one
because you're not
bloated and you feel good.
And that is the measure.
These bars are sweet, filling
genuinely good tasting.
Flavors include red velvet, apple
cinnamon, chocolate chip, plenty
more. They're all great.
If you're trying to clean up your
die but need something convenient to
grab these are
a solid option.
Give them a try at paleovalley.com,
use code TUCKER at checkout for 20%
off your first order.
Paleovally.com code TuckER,
20% of your first purchase.
So what, I mean, because you are a
Westerner, you do have a certain
advantage. I mean you're an English
speaking Westerna from the British
Isles and you're on television.
So you're the subject of an
assassination attempt by a
supposedly Western government, one
that's armed by Western governments.
What's your recourse?
What do you do after they try and
kill you, but they fail?
Well, that's a very good question.
Obviously, I am an
English-speaking white westerner,
which gives me a certain advantage,
a certain privilege.
I mean, I have to say that just
over a week after
our very close shave,
our dear colleagues and friends in
the field weren't so lucky.
Fatima Fatuni, Ali Shuaib and
Mohammed Fatuni were
killed in a
targeted strike by Israelis
just after they've been reporting.
In the south so i
mean this is the kind of the
conditions that journalists are
working in on on
the ground in terms of the recourse
well um i work for russian
state television um which of course
means that the my my own government
the british government and
don't like me.
In fact, they have already,
instead of supporting me, they've
been put, they've persecuted me.
I was detained on a
family visit last July
at Heathrow airport.
I was met by counter-terror police
off the airplane.
They took me away for interrogation.
They quizzed me over my relations to
Russia, the Russian state,
working for Russian state
television, also about
my work here in Lebanon, my
associations or connections to
Hezbollah, my connections to
Ansarallah in Yemen because I've
reported from Yemen, Hashdol
Shabi, and my
work in in Donbass.
I spent two years in the field in
Donbas on the Russian side so they
were very interested in that.
And they're still
now currently investigating me
for potential terrorist
activity based on my
journalism.
So I don't expect anything from
them and some
friends of mine at Declassified UK,
British media organization,
well they inquired, they asked the
British government for comment after
this assassination attempt,
and they just simply said...
Summarizing here, paraphrasing that
they said something along the lines
of the Foreign
Secretary has given
Britain's position on the
Middle East in a statement to
the Commons on Tuesday.
That was all they said.
They didn't address the specifics of
my case.
They haven't commented on it.
They haven't offered any kind of
support whatsoever.
Even even the British Embassy here
in Lebanon hasn't
contacted me. The only support that
I've had, I've had lots of you
know, love and well wishes from
individuals and organizations across
the world for which we're, you know
we're incredibly grateful and
thankful for.
But the only people, the only
country that's actually given me
strong and solid support has been
Russia.
Are you a British passport holder?
Ambassador.
I'm a British Passport holder, yes.
So you're a-
subject, so this is even though
you don't live there most of the
time, you have family there, you are
a citizen, but
the British government is taking the
side of the Israeli military over
its own citizens?
Well, that's how it seems to me,
yes, not only taking the side of the
Israelis, but they're helping
provide the weapons
and the ammunition and the political
and military support to carry out
such strikes.
So, you know, somewhere along that
chain, I mean, we know it was an
F-16 and a GBU-38
made American supplied,
but Britain is well involved in that
supply chain.
So some of the kind of
the add-on equipment that enabled
them to carry out that strike
against me is almost certainly
provided by the British government
without a doubt.
How does that, I don't
understand since both
Britain and the United States fought
against the Nazis and lost
hundreds of thousands of their own
men doing it.
I don't really see where the moral
culpability is here.
Why would Britain and the
Unites States have some
duty to become subjects of the
Israeli government?
Where does that come from?
Well, I mean, there's
a long history of, you know, the two
biggest supporters of Israel have
traditionally been the United States
and Britain.
And, you can trace this back to the
formation of the state of Israel.
Now, of course, they have their
own interests in the region.
They use Israel as a
proxy force for its colonialist,
imperialist expansion plans
for the region, if you look at
what's happening on the ground now.
The reason that we reported on the
Which is, is.
What you're seeing now is the
fourth expulsion of
1.2 million Lebanese
people that have been forced from
their land, forced from there homes
and they're now forcibly
displaced. We describe this in
Lebanon, we talk about it as an
ethnic cleansing operation on
a scale far larger than
the Nakba.
That's the of course the
hundreds of thousands of
Palestinians that were forced from
their homes on the creation
of the state of Israel.
So the situation here is...
It's simply astonishing,
and you know, 370,000
of those forcibly displaced to
children.
So, but behind that is this
attempt by Israel to grab that land.
Now, not only are they
forcing people out of that area
south of the Letarni River,
they've extended that now to south
of Zirani River, so we're talking
some 40 kilometers from the Israeli
border that they've pushed people
out that area.
Now,
The Israelis have been very open.
Israel Katz, the Defense Secretary,
has said that we want the land.
We're going to, you know, they've
said that they want to create a
security buffer zone or whatever
terminology they used to describe
it, but these plans have been long
in the making. You go back in
history and Israel has invaded
and tried to take that area, they
think it's their biblical right.
We're talking about the Greater
Israel Project, which I know you
know fall well about after your
conversation with Ambassador
Huckabee.
And it kind of
reappears in different guises
over the years.
The most latest was the Trump
economic zone.
This was announced back in,
I think, August last year.
Around that time, Tom Barrack, the
US envoy, arrived here
in Lebanon.
And you might remember this.
Soundbite from him because he spoke
at the presidential palace to a
group of journalists and there was a
bit of a melee and he described them
as animalistic.
And he was condemned for,
you know, this was seen as an
incredibly racist comment to make
towards Lebanese journalists who
were doing their job in the field,
holding people to account,
questioning him.
But behind that, he laid out this
plan for the Trump economic zone,
which meant that hundreds of
thousands of people would be forced
from their homes permanently.
Now it is dressed up.
This is going to be a
regeneration project.
We're going to create new homes.
We are going create jobs, we're
going to create roads, we are going
to create infrastructure, we going
to make the area safe.
But it meant that people that have
lived on this land for
generations, these are their homes.
These are not just, you know, dots
on a map.
These are homes where people have
lived on that land for generations
are going to be turfed out.
And nobody really paid attention to
it at the time. Of course, we did as
journalists on the ground.
And you know people talk about
They say that the Gaza model is now
coming to Lebanon.
They've spoken about it in terms,
I think Smotrich said, we're going
to turn Dahir, the southern suburbs
of Beirut, into Khan Yunis.
And then they've used Beit Hanun and
Raffa.
Israel Kat said that they're going
to destroy all of these villages
that they call front line villages.
And I can tell you now, we've
been here for two years.
Those villages are largely already
destroyed.
The south of Lebanon already looks
like Gaza, whole villages completely
lie in ruins, no reconstruction
plan.
And over the last 15 months, we've
seen Israel break that ceasefire.
And we call about talk about a
ceasefire from November 2024, but
there was never a cease fire.
You can't have a cease-fire when
only one side stops firing.
And okay, 15,000, more than 15,
000 violations over the past 15
months. And this has included
the rigging and destroying of
homes, the drone strikes,
targeted assassinations, the use of
chemical spray to destroy
crops.
We witnessed and filmed all this,
the use of white phosphorus.
There's a place called Bleda, a
village very close to the border,
now during olive harvesting
season, we went to make a film
there. The Israelis refused to
allow the farmers to tend to their
land unless they gave them all
of the contact details and the names
of who was going into the fields
while we were there, and they
started bulldozing the olive groves.
These are olive grove that are older
than the state of Israel.
So this isn't something
new.
What we're seeing now, the
escalation on March the 2nd has been
going on for a very, very
long time. Now, you asked me why
Britain and the United States would
support that. Well, they use Israel
as their kind of...
Proxy force in the
area they refer to as the Middle
East. We call it West Asia here and
they use it to
to grab the land.
The Greater Israel Project suits
Israel but it suits Britain and the
United States because this is
a land of great wealth
and resources and they want to
extract that wealth and
they will extract the resources and
use it for their own gain.
And of course they want strategic
control across the whole of the
region.
We've seen that with what
happened in Syria.
We can see now with the bombing of
of Iran.
We can see what happened in Gaza.
All of these have taken place,
not just with the connivance of
the United States and Britain, but
with that active involvement.
So this is the kind of,
this is what we're happening now,
you can see signs.
Along the airport road here in
Beirut that they
say made it made in the United
States, made in USA and that's how
they see the bombs that are
falling on them here.
They're made in the united states,
they're made in Britain and they're
the root cause of the death
and destruction that's taking place
across this region.
Israel fires the bullets but the
guns well and truly loaded by
Britain and the United States.
So what's in your toothpaste?
If you're using the brand you grew
up with, you probably don't want to
know. The ingredients likely include
fluoride, something called SLS,
glycerin, foaming agents.
It's a chemical cocktail.
Van Man's toothpaste is different.
Their miracle tooth powder is
changing everything, and people are
ditching traditional toothpaste
filled with chemicals by the
thousands.
Van Man toothpaste uses ingredients
with the same mineral structure as
your teeth.
That re-mineralizes them and
strengthens your enamel naturally.
No fluoride at all, and totally
edible. You could put it on toast,
not that you'd want to, but you
could.
People who use it report wetter
teeth, less plaque, they wake up
without that gross film on their
gums, and here's the amazing part,
vivid dreams are back.
You dream clearly when you stop
coating your mouth in Florida every
night. Did you know that?
Pretty amazing.
Tells you a lot.
So make the switch.
Visit vanman.shop slash
Tucker. Use the code Tucker for 15%
off your first order.
Vanman dot shop slash Tucker, use
the code tucker, 15%
Off.
Vanman, real ingredients,
zero exceptions.
Well, since you mentioned, and I
have to ask you about a small point
that has bothered me for many years,
and that's the Israeli policy of
cutting down olive trees, some of
which are hundreds and hundreds, up
to a thousand years old,
and of course, they're, right,
they're central to the ancient
economy of the Levant, but they're
also beautiful.
Yeah. And they're revered almost
by the people who are actually from
there, not the ones from Poland who
pretend they're from there but the
people actually are there.
Why would the Israeli
government chainsaw
or bulldoze olive trees.
That seems evil to me.
I don't understand the explanation
for it.
Well, that's the only way to
look at it. Of course, it's evil,
but I think
these, like you said, these olive
groves, some of them are thousands
of years old. I think the oldest in
Lebanon is something like 6,000
years old, but it's the lifeblood
of Lebanon.
It's a symbol of...
Lebanese cultural heritage,
identity, and the people here are
very, very connected to their land.
They're deeply connected to to their
land. And you know, this is
the lifeblood, not just for the the
south of Lebanon, where
you know the farmers will
will harvest their olive groves.
Tobacco is a big,
a huge crop here, but this is a
lifebloody for all of Lebanon.
Now if you can disconnect people
from their land and their culture,
then of course you can
you can take it over and that's
what they've been doing not just by
bulldozing it, bombing it,
but by spraying these chemicals that
will make sure that these crops will
never be able to grow on the land
again and they can just brush them
aside, they can build houses,
they Can build settlements there
just like they did when on
the formation of the state of
Israel. They're building these
illegal settlements everywhere and
that is
in in lebanon they're building
They want to.
That's their aim.
Yeah. I mean, you look at the
Greater Israel Project itself.
Now, I mentioned Yahrun
earlier. This is the place
where the mosque and the church were
destroyed.
Now, earlier this year, a few months
before
the escalation on March the 2nd,
this group of settlers came in
across the border into or very
close to Yahroun and they planted
trees.
And the message was, this, I
can't remember the exact terminology
that they used, but this was them
planting their roots in
Lebanese territory, and
they believe that Lebanese territory
biblically belongs to them.
Now, you know, you look back a few
years ago, and this could have been
seen as a conspiracy theory or
a fringe kind
of movement, but this is now right
at the heart of the Israeli
government.
Smotrich and Ben-Gavir are advocates
of the Greater Israel Project.
Benjamin Netanyahu himself is
a supporter of the Greater Israel
Project. This isn't kind of like a
fantasy. This is happening now.
It's unfolding in
real time in front of our very
eyes.
So they
have some
rabbis in Israel that justify
this religiously as well.
They will say that this is the land
that belongs to them according to
Holy Scripture.
And this is why we're seeing this,
this whole scale destruction.
That's what it was around over the
last 15 months.
They say it was about destroying
Hezbollah, but it's not,
it's not the, you're seeing whole
kind of settlements lying
under rubble. My beloved is from a
village in, in the South and
her entire
village has pretty much been
reduced to rubble, her family home
rebuilt, destroyed,
rebuilt, destroyed so many times.
And this is.
You know, very common for the people
in that part
of the world.
And again,
Israel has occupied Lebanon and
after the ceasefire in November
2024, it built five
military bases inside Lebanese
sovereign territory.
We filmed them and rather
than scaling them
back, Israel was expanding the
construction of those military
posts illegally.
In breach of UN resolution
1701, in breach of
international law, the Lebanese
government asked them to leave
Lebanese sovereign territory, and of
course they just simply refused and
they pushed further and further
into Lebanese Sovereign Territory.
Now the interesting thing, and I
don't know whether your viewers will
be aware of this, Um.
And many people don't know,
but there isn't really an official
border between Israel and
Lebanon. There's no officially
agreed border.
We have the Blue Line, which was
established by the United Nations.
This was after Israel
was forced out in 2000,
and this line is supposed to be the
demarcation point that Israel
is not supposed to encroach further
across
this line.
So Israel sees a lot of this land
as belonging,
there was the 1923 mandate
line when it was the British
mandate of Palestine.
There was a kind of border drawn
up then which Israel inhabited in
1948 but has never really agreed to.
The armistice in 1949.
Didn't again agree those
borders.
So Israel sees fit to push
forward at
will and it's done so with total
impunity of course.
There's no kind of international
outcry about the destruction of
these villages and settlements or
the use of chemical weapons, the use
of white phosphorus or the
assassination of
individuals in drone strikes or the
killing of paramedics, the murder
of journalists, all of these things
have been happening.
For many, many years.
The world is maybe paying more
attention to it now.
We've had the western journalists
arriving in the country since
March the 2nd, of course.
The major news networks have arrived
and they're kind of surprised at
what they're seeing. They're seeing
this for the first time.
But this has been going on for a
very, very long time.
And I say this is a bit of a
failing, I would say, of the...
Major media organizations, because
had they been on the ground in
Lebanon for the past 15 months, they
would have seen this unfolding.
And you know, maybe the situation
would be very different from what
it is now, as it is,
they weren't there.
And the Lebanese journalists were
reporting the people that live
on that land were crying
for help and nobody was listening.
I have to ask, so you are covering
this on the ground in
Lebanon, living and working at the
center of all this and as noted,
almost got killed for it, but you're
working for a Russian news agency.
You've clearly been a journalist a
long time.
You look over 40, so probably
a long-time.
How did you wind up working
for Russian news agencies?
Like, why aren't you a BBC reporter?
What was your path?
The MI5 would never claim to work
with me.
No, they weren't!
There's no chance, no chance.
I mean, I wouldn't work for
the BBC on a personal level.
We've met some BBC journalists here
and they've been very pleasant, very
nice and I've had all the
journalists from the major
networks, there's individual
journalists, I have no problem
with them.
How I ended up working for
RT, for Russia today,
is I was working for a
newspaper before I
entered the world of broadcast
journalism. I was the international
editor of a national daily newspaper
in Britain for many years.
When the Ukraine conflict started,
um the special military operation.
I was covering that and
I went to the western part
of Ukraine to
to pick up there was a couple of
stories I was chasing there.
I ended up in Lvov.
The Ukrainians tried to um
to kidnap me and I managed
to make my escape from
from there back out um back
out through Poland and then to
Germany.
Wait, I'm going to ask you to pause,
why did they do that?
Why did they try to kidnap you, the
Ukrainians?
Well, simply because I
was a journalist that wasn't towing
their narrative,
and the Ukraine conflict is the
most propagandized war in
history, in my view.
I mean, you look at what happened in
even the Iraq war, there was kind
of that space within the media field
to criticize
your government's policy.
When it came to Ukraine,
that window or that gap narrowed
to the point where...
It was impossible because
there was no space
to offer anything that was different
from the narrative of the Western
governments, the British government,
the Ukrainian government.
So if you were going there to
actually do some proper journalism,
and I say that because, you know,
with all
due respect to those organizations,
the BBC, CNN,
Sky News, uh you
know the the times the telegraph
channel for they were doing these
kind of um
They were all saying the exact
same thing, they were taking it in
turns to stand on the top of the
same hotel roof in Kiev or Lvov and
repeat the line, repeat the
line, but they weren't actually
seeing what was
the reality on the
ground.
They were just stenographers
essentially, these kind
of
copy and paste reports,
and It reached kind of insane
levels in Britain.
I'm sure it was the same with the
United States, but Britain was, they
started demonizing Vladimir Putin.
One of the craziest reports I saw
was that Vladimir Putin
has an
assistant that follows him around
with a briefcase and every time he
goes to the toilet they collect his
feces and urine so his opponents
can't run any kind of
tests on them. I mean it got to,
you know, completely insane levels
and anytime you were reporting so
I ended up at Russia today
after that because I saw that
my independence as
a journalist and my ability
to report on the truth had
completely disappeared.
It was impossible.
The only way to do that was
to go to Russia and
work for RT.
We have one
of our logos, Question More,
and that's what we do.
I always say, question more,
question us. That's the role of a
journalist. So.
I ended up working for RT,
I ended up working two years in
Donbass on the Russian side,
and I was seeing something
completely different from the
narrative that was being played out
in the West.
I was seeing war crimes committed
daily by the Ukrainians
against a civilian population.
When I was there, they called it
Donetsk Roulette.
You never know when a missile
might strike you.
And I was seeing attacks on
marketplaces, for example.
27 people killed body
parts everywhere.
These were like babushkas,
dadushkas. Old men, old women, the
poorest people in
that part of
the city.
Um your homemade fruit and
vegetables from from their home just
obliterated you know arms and legs
uh everywhere i was seeing hospitals
that were that were struck
bus bus stops that were being
attacked you know so i mean i could
talk about that for a long time i
spoke about it at the united nations
security council um i
gave testimony of of what i'd seen
the failures of Minsk 1
and Minsk 2 and the
path to peace.
What we're seeing, and what
I always say, is what we were seeing
in that
part in Donbass,
is the same playbook
that we're saying in Gaza, the same
playbook here in Lebanon.
These are the most powerful
countries in the world,
waging war using the most
sophisticated technology, the most
powerful weapons against some
of the poorest, most vulnerable
people in the world.
They can't fight back.
They don't have the arms.
They don t have the weapons.
The people of Gaza, the people of
Lebanon, they weren't sent high
marks or storm shadows or
these advanced weapons.
These were sent to their oppressors
to massacre them.
This is what's happening
and it's the very same forces.
In Donbas, it was very simple for
me as a journalist.
It was the people that wanted peace,
the people who wanted to be able to
speak their own language, Russian,
people that want to be able to
practice their own culture and
traditions, if they identified as
Russian, and pretty much
that was it.
You could put it really
as simply as that.
But then...
And the Ukrainian government decided
to wage a war against its own
people.
I know for some this went back to
the start of the SMO, but this has
a much, much longer history,
starting way back in 2014, the
Maidan coup.
You know, all of these things people
forget about now.
Conveniently, including the media.
The media actually made them forget
about it because, you know, one day
there was a neo-Nazi problem in
Ukraine.
You know, the Azov and the right
sector were carrying
out these horrific actions,
these horrific killings.
They were terrorizing the people.
And the next day, all of a sudden,
Ukraine is a paragon of liberal
democracy.
It's incredible.
But people aren't getting the truth.
So This is why I ended
up at RT because
the space to do proper journalism
just wasn't afforded to me anywhere
else. None of the British press.
Like I said, I kind of semi-joked,
but MI5 would never allow me to work
for the BBC or for
any of the other major news
organizations.
And, you know, I have to say with
Russia today, with RT...
I have complete freedom to
report exactly what
I want and nobody tells me what
to say, nobody tells where
I can film, nobody tells who
I can speak to, who I should speak
to.
I have total journalistic freedom
and I'm very
happy working for RT.
I'm proud to work for RT And
we always say
that here on the ground, because,
you know, obviously,
I came.
Kind of sprung into the into the
limelight after what happened to me
and um but it's not about
me journalists should never become
the story unwittingly um
i did but we always say that you
know the our
job is to raise the voices of the
people of the of this land and we
always say that our mic is a
tribune for the people and it
will continue to be a tribume for
the as long as we
remain in the field.
It must be such a strange experience
for you since you've been in
the British media for a long time,
conventional media, a newspaper in
a country that reads newspapers
famously.
All of a sudden to have this
perspective where
you have more freedom to
do journalism, to straightforward
journalism at Russia
today than you had at
a British newspaper.
I mean, what is that as someone who
I assume you were raised in the UK?
Yeah. What is that like?
Well, the media
field in Britain, and
I think it's not just in Britain but
if you look at the Western
countries, it's
very concentrated, it is owned by a
very small group of people
who own and control the
media. They control what you say,
they control the narrative.
So, but I think that the
change was that the
owners of these media organizations
are now more and more
forcefully pushing their view
and their narrative.
And you see it permeating through
every word that's spoken on
British television.
You see it written in every
single word in every newspaper.
There's no divergence.
They're all uniform.
So, you know, of course, Russia,
people in the West think that Russia
is some kind of...
Authoritarian dictatorship that
we're living under the jackpot of
Vladimir Putin.
But you've been to Moscow, you know
anything but
the truth. It couldn't be further
from the truth, you see
people, I mean, there are very
educated people, they are
rich again.
We were talking about Lebanon
earlier, having this rich culture
and history.
I mean Russia, come on, I
mean, I don't know any other nation
on earth that has such a rich
culture and history, you know,
Shostakovich, Dostoevsky,
Prokofiev, Yuri Gagarin,
they put the first human being
in space,
Meddileyev, the founder of the
table of the elements,
these huge figures in the field of
science, of literature, of art,
of music.
And you go to any bar
in in in Moscow and
and you can sit down there within
five minutes you've had one
of the most intelligent
political or cultural conversations
that you've ever had sitting over
a cold pint of of Guinness
and for those that think that
people are too afraid to criticize
Putin let me tell you they're not
they're, not I've heard it
myself and you know the same
the same kind of criticisms you hear
in every country
anywhere in the world.
They're not afraid to express those
views. They don't necessarily hold
them. Vladimir Putin is incredibly
popular, and he's incredibly popular
for a very good reason, is that
people remember the days
before Putin became president,
and they remember it was a very,
very dark time in the country.
And after the collapse of the Soviet
Union, up until Vladimir Putin came
to power, there wasn't really
that kind of national stability.
I mean, Russia is obviously a huge
country, 11 time zones, I think
it is. So to hold it together is
incredibly difficult.
But Vladimir Putin bought that
stability. He made Russia into what
it is today. And this is a strong,
economically thriving, independent
country that is actually,
despite what the West says, You
know, it still has.
These good relations with other
countries on the world stage.
It's not isolated by any
stretch of the imagination.
It is only isolated if you think the
world is the western powers.
So there is
this freedom to criticize,
but of course it's hugely
popular. And, you
know, I think people in the West...
Find that very difficult to
understand just
how popular Putin
is in Russia.
Everything you're saying is true.
I've seen it multiple times.
Even, for example,
RT is banned in the United
States, it's banned in Europe.
In Russia, you've probably seen,
but Vladimir Putin holds a, every
year he holds a Q&A for
journalists, for members of the
public.
Every year the BBC is there.
Steve Rosenberg asks a question, he
tries to get a gotcha every
year. He fails every year, but he
keeps giving it a go.
But the BBC is allowed to operate
freely inside inside
Russia. I couldn't do the same in
Britain. They're trying to arrest me
They would they would arrest you
about freedom of press if you tried
if you practiced what you're
doing now in your home country
Yes.
If I took an RT microphone into
London and started trying to
interview people, or if I stood
in front of a camera with an RT
microphone and started to give
a report, I would be
arrested.
We're banned.
We're treated as, I don't
know, like foreign agents.
So it would be unlawful for us
to work there.
We could be jailed, sanctioned,
a whole host of...
Things can happen. So we don't have
that freedom to operate inside
Britain.
I always, you know, this is
something that always amazes me
because you know the
Russian state television was banned
in Europe and
America because you know we're
propagandists or whatever, the
Kremlin media machine or you know
these kind of tired old tropes that
we hear, which is deeply
rooted in Russophobia,
but what they're really saying is
that the people of Europe and and
America are stupid.
You know, people are
able to disseminate
facts from fiction, they're able to
watch a news report and decide
whether it's propaganda or whether
it is true. They can make that
decision themselves and they should
be able to make that decisions
themselves in a free and democratic
country that operates
with freedom of speech and
freedom of the press.
So, you know,
it always strikes me as quite
bizarre that they keep saying, well,
we uphold freedom of the press.
Well, in fact, the European Union
has sanctioned
a journalist, someone I knew.
No, Hussain Dourou, who is
a journalist for Red Media.
They sanctioned him because
of his work.
They said he's closed.
I think they accused him of
something to do with the Russian
state, but it was because of is
reporting on.
On Palestine, so there's
no way that they uphold freedom of
the press.
I myself am being investigated for
potential terrorist activities based
on my journalism, nothing else.
That's it for my journalistic
reports.
So where's the
press freedom?
Can I walk into
um into the united states
can i can i you know freely walk
around and start interviewing people
can i interview donald trump can i
sit down and speak to the people on
the ground of course not with band
it's an absurdity
it is but press freedom is
alive and kicking
And it's also a little
bit bewildering.
It's surprising for me and
it's an ominous sign I would
say as an American to
see people arrested in Britain for
criticizing Israel.
Why would it be illegal for a
Britain to criticize Israel?
What does Israel have to do with the
UK? And by the way, it was Israeli
terror groups who murdered British
citizens, British soldiers, British
Diplomats.
That's exact, and many others, and
they murdered a lot of Brits and
murdered them with their hands
slowly. In some cases, blew them up
with bombs, but true terrorist acts,
and the guy who did it later became
the prime minister, Menachem Begin.
So actually, Israel owes a
great debt to the UK, which is
responsible for its formation in the
first place, as you know.
So why in the world would
British citizens be banned
from criticizing Israel?
They owe nothing to Israel.
What is this?
Well, it's a bizarre dystopian
situation.
You've probably seen, but in
Britain,
I guess maybe six months ago, the
government moved to ban a group
called Palestine Action.
And these were protesters
that were throwing paint at
airplanes or whatever.
They were trying to stop a genocide.
And Britain prescribed it as a
terrorist organization, I think
against all the legal advice that
they were given. They ignored that
and they ahead.
And it became illegal to even
support or hold up placards saying
I support Palestine action.
So they were arresting like
80, 90 year old women.
They were dragging them away
and charging them as
terrorists under terrorism
offenses.
So I mean Britain has obviously it's
invested in.
Israel heavily invested in Israel
clearly because it was Britain
really that was behind the formation
of the state of Israel in the first
place. You can trace it back to the
Balfour Declaration where they drew
a line in the sand and gave a land
that didn't belong to them to
another people whose land it wasn't.
They gave away the land that
belonged to the people indigenous to
that land.
So I think, you know, they talk
about this historical debt owed to
Israel.
Now, of course, you can go to
Germany and some of the European
countries, and of course they talk
of the Holocaust,
and they bear a heavy burden and
responsibility for that, or they
feel that.
And again, there's this kind of
historical debt that they feel.
But in Britain now, it's
kind of moved way beyond
that.
And like you said, they were
in the early days in
the formation of the state of
Israel, they were attacking Brits,
killing Brits blowing up hotels.
So this kind of
unraveled support where you
can't even criticize Israel,
there's no space.
Any criticism of Israel is now
deemed either antisemitic,
an act of terror, unlawful,
and it means that you're ostracized
from society, you're labeled an
anti-Semite, you're labeled a racist
and I mean, the Britain's objective
is, I mean Israel is an
outpost for Anglo-American
imperialist,
what they want to gain out
of the region. So it acts as this
kind of Anglo-imperialist outpost
and it will back Israel
militarily to the hilt.
It will back them politically to
the hill. But of course, they're
using it to strategically control
the entire of the
Middle East. I mean this is their
historical myth.
I mean, everything
that happens in this region is
because of the historical mess of
the British and the French,
you know, back in the time of
the Sykes-Picot, carving
up of that part of the world, just
arbitrarily drawing lines, okay, you
can have this part, you can have
that part.
And you know the legacy of
that lives on today,
which is in fact why as a British
journalist, I'd say, of Irish
origin.
You know, certainly as a Western
journalist, I have a
historical debt to the people of
this land because
of what my country has inflicted
upon them. And I see that
as part of my duty
as a journalist, not to
just fall in line behind my own
government, not to be a stenographer
for power, but
to expose to the world what's
happening here on the ground in
Lebanon and in other countries
and for every bomb that
falls on Lebanon
and there have been many of them, I
can tell you, but every bomb that
falls on Lebanon is a bomb
that is supplied by the United
States, a bomb is supplied
by Britain.
Israel just simply fires the bullets
that they're supplied and it's been
carrying out these actions with
the support and complicity of
Britain and the United States and
other Western countries.
Do your former colleagues in the
British media feel shame as
they continue their stenography and
see you speaking freely and risking
your life to do it?
They should do.
They should feel a great
sense of shame.
But now, I don't know whether they
do. Like I said, on a personal
level, I've met the individual
journalists from the major news
organizations and they've been very,
very gracious and very pleasant
as individuals.
But they all fall in
line with the same narrative.
Even the journalists that are coming
here, they'll describe...
Dahir, which is the southern suburbs
of Beirut, that entire area has
been evacuated.
We're talking an area between 500
and 800,000 people.
Mm.
And that whole area has been
evacuated.
It's bombed every single day
without fail.
Fighter jets roaring overhead,
drones overhead, civilian buildings
being destroyed. Now for them, this
is the southern suburbs of Beirut.
They call it a Hezbollah
stronghold.
Now, okay, that use of language
is not an accident.
It is deliberate.
They call it Hezbullah stronghold
because it justifies the bombing of
that area. But this isn't a
Hezbollah stronghold.
This is where we live.
These are the coffee shops where we
meet our friends, these are the
places we go shopping, this
is an area vibrant,
full of life, people's homes,
this kind of thing.
Yeah, the Western
media play a very pernicious role,
in fact, in what
I believe is this manufacturing
of consent.
Because outside of that, Tahir is
just a place on a map that gets
bombed.
Lebanon is a war zone.
That's how they describe it.
Lebanon isn't a warzone, as we
already discussed. Lebanon is as a
land of rich culture, rich
tradition, rich history, full of
the most amazing people
you could ever meet anywhere
in the world.
The same with the south of Lebanon,
they say, well, all these areas
south of the Latani.
They're all Hezbollah supporters.
I mean, of
course there's strong support for
Hezbollah in those areas
because they see them as the only
organization that is standing up
and fighting against Israel,
that is defending their land,
their territory.
Hezballah was only born in
the mid-1980s.
Now, the people of...
Lebanon don't have like a devolution
or a fantasy of, you
know, or a predisposed to
using weapons and guns.
You know, it's not that they enjoy
going around shooting people.
They were formed as an armed militia
exactly to defend their
land, the same as in
Ireland, the same as, in fact, you
can pick any country that's
come under attack from
um you know from the from the
western powers from Israel from
their neighbors yeah that's
the origins of these organizations
but to call it Hezbollah land
which is some of the description
that we're we're finding this is
as we said the land that Jesus
walked in it's a land
rich um in
culture and history,
but the Western journalists are kind
of seeing it very much, or
speaking about it, or writing about
it very, much in those terms.
We hear the same kind of, it's
like these dog-whistled, frigger
words, you know, ran back.
The Iranian-backed
militia,
the Hezbollah strongholds, all these
kind of things, the terminology
that they use, and it's absolutely
deliberate to justify
Israel bombing those lands.
That's all it is.
So, whether they're embarrassed
about writing that or not, I don't
know. I think it's very difficult
to get a job in the British media if
you don't write those
kind of lines or
you don't speak them into a camera
now.
And Noam Chomsky, who
back in, I guess,
the 90s was interviewing a
British journalist, Andrew Martin, I
think he hit the nail on the head
when he said, okay, I'm not
necessarily saying you don't
believe what you're saying,
but if you didn't believe what you
said, you wouldn't be sitting where
you are now.
I think that's it.
It's true, right?
I mean, you know, you're not going
to get a job unless you believe
those things, unless you're prepared
to say them or write them.
Um, so whether they're
embarrassed or not, I don't know.
And to be honest, I didn't care very
much.
They may not be capable of it.
So my my last question you don't
like talking about yourself, but is
about you So Israel tried
to assassinate you they failed
Just barely I
Can't imagine interviews like
this make them
Less inclined to assassinating
you to try again.
Are you gonna stay in Lebanon?
Absolutely.
100% without doubt.
I'll stay in Lebanon.
Lebanon is my home.
My beloved is
here in Lebanon, my life is here in
there. I always say look,
Lebanon isn't my country but Lebanon
and the Lebanese people belong
in my heart.
And yeah,
I'll forever be in the service
of the Lebanese people.
They've been good enough to host me
in their country.
And I hope that my
journalism does them justice and I
hope my presence does
them just as I always remember.
And it's always important to
remember that I'm a guest in
this land.
So no, I have no intention of
leaving. I have no intention to stop
reporting.
We've already been back to the front
line. And just two days
after the attack, we made sure that
we went out because we're not going
to be silenced.
And if they think that we're going
to be leaving the field,
then...
They're very much mistaken.
What a remarkable conversation.
It is one of the great countries and
most beautiful countries in
the world.
Top five in my opinion, top three.
So I'm grateful you're there to
chronicle what's being done to it
in our name with our weapons.
It's really evil.
So anyway, Steve Sweeney, thank you
very much for doing this.
I appreciate it.
A pleasure, thank you.